<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Canzonets. Or Little short songs to foure voyces: celected out of the best and approued Italian authors. By Thomas Morley, Gent. of her Maiesties chappell. Cantus [-Altus, -Tenor, -Bassus].</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110070</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845687</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845687</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07742)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 439:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Canzonets. Or Little short songs to foure voyces: celected out of the best and approued Italian authors. By Thomas Morley, Gent. of her Maiesties chappell. Cantus [-Altus, -Tenor, -Bassus].</title>
                  <author>Morley, Thomas, 1557-1603?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p. : music  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Peter Short, dwelling on Bredstreet hill at the signe of the Star &amp; are there to be sold,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Four partbooks, each with separate dated title page and register.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ B-C⁴; [A]⁴ B-C⁴; [A]⁴ B-C⁴; [A]⁴ B-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Songs, Italian --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Part-songs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:1"/>
                  <p>CANZONETS. OR LITTLE SHORT SONGS TO FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>OYCES: CELECTED OVT OF the beſt and approued Italian Authors. BY THOMAS MORLEY, Gent. of her Maieſties Chappell.</p>
                  <p>CANTVS.</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by Peter Short, dwelling on Bredſtreet hill at the ſigne of the Star &amp; are there to be ſold. 1597.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL <hi>MAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER HENRIE TAPS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FIELD</hi> CITIZEN AND GRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CER OF THE CITTIE OF LONDON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all enormities reigning (in men of reaſonable capacitie) none maketh them more deformed then the monſter Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? whoſe outragious cruelty hath Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomorphoſed, <hi>friendſhip</hi> into <hi>emnity, familiarity,</hi> into <hi>contempt, Loue</hi> into <hi>hatred:</hi> and generally all <hi>good</hi> into <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> The remembrance whereof, hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtirred my ſences to haue your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in remembrance, for diuers and many curteſies, from you to my ſelfe and my friends often receaued: And that in bounty ſo farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as my offer of requitall can no way counteruaile. But as migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>Alexander,</hi> for tenne talents giuen to the reliefe of a poore craftes man, was thankefully contented with the receipt of a ſimple roote. So J hartily intreat you, to accept theſe poore Canzonets, by me collected from diuers excellent Jtalian Authours, for the honeſt recreation of your ſelfe and others: Such as in my ſimple iudgment are worthie the collecting, but much more worthy hauing the Habit of ſo worthy a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, in whoſe acceptance they ſhall bee ſo well entertained, as were their maſters preſent to behold it, they woulde not onely thinke them happely beſtowed, but alſo yeeld me thankes for choiſe of their patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. And thus crauing your worthy acceptance, but reſting ſtil your debtor, J take my leaue as yours to commaund.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>THOMAS MORLEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:3"/>
                  <head>A TABLE OF ALL THE CANZONETS contained in this BOOKE.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>NOw that each creature. I</item>
                     <item>Since that the time of fleeting. II.</item>
                     <item>Lady let me behold euer your beauty. III.</item>
                     <item>Lo Lady for your loue. IIII.</item>
                     <item>Fine dainty girle delightſome. V.</item>
                     <item>White Lillies be her cheekes. VI.</item>
                     <item>Flora faire loue I languiſh. VII</item>
                     <item>My hart why haſt thou taken. VIII.</item>
                     <item>Still it frieth. IX.</item>
                     <item>Kiſſe me mine only Iewell. X.</item>
                     <item>Faine would I die for very ſhame &amp; ſorrow. XI.</item>
                     <item>Come ſhepheards god. XII.</item>
                     <item>Weary and windles running. XIII.</item>
                     <item>Miraculous loues wounding. XIIII.</item>
                     <item>Faſt by a brooke <hi>I</hi> layd me. XV.</item>
                     <item>VVhen loe by breake of morning. XVI.</item>
                     <item>Long hath my loue. XVII.</item>
                     <item>Pearle, Chriſtall, Gold and Ruby. XVIII.</item>
                     <item>Ceaſe ſhepheards. XIX.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Daphne</hi> the bright. XX.</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:3"/>
                  <head>I. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow that each creature takes his reſt and ſleepeth. ij. More wretched I then any worme that creepeth. Alone all comefortles vntill the morrow. Go recounting my ſorrow: ij. Goe recounting my ſor╌row: Goe recounting my ſorrow, ij. Go recounting my ſorrow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:4"/>
                  <head>II. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of fleeting, From thee is come my ſweeting: Since that the time of fleeting, Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee is come my ſweeting. Doe but a kiſſe award me: And for my ſeruiſe ſo you ſhall reward me, you ſhall reward me. Do but a kiſſe award me, And for my ſeruiſe ſo you ſhall reward me, you ſhall reward me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:4"/>
                  <head>III. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ady let me behold, ij. Lady let me behold, euer your beauty: Lady let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. ii. Lady let me beholde euer your beauty. And ſeeke yee not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me ſo to enſtrang it, Since time to come may change it: Since time to come may change it. And ſeeke ye not from me ſo to enſtrange it, Since time to come may chang it, Since time to come may change it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:5"/>
                  <head>IIII. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>O Lady for your loue I feele this burning, I feele this burning, Lo Lady for your loue I feele this burning, I feele this burning. And no whit grieue you, ij. for this flaming fuell, When you deny me (O cruell.) Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a thouſand skorns one ſweet eye turning, one ſweet eye turning, when you deny me, (O cruell.) After a thouſand skorns one ſweet eye turning, one ſweet eye, turning.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:5"/>
                  <head>V. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ine dainty girle delightſom, You be my Loadſtar lightſom, my Loadſtar lightſom, fine dainty girle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighſom, you be my loadſtar lightſom, my loadſtar lightſom. To you my hart ay turneth, when in the tempeſt, when in the tempeſt, of fierce loue fierce loue it burneth, To you my hart ay turneth, when in the tempeſt, when in the tempeſt of fierce loue fierce loue it burneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:6"/>
                  <head>VI. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hite Lillies be her cheekes &amp; ſhamefaſt Roſes, ii. White Lillies be her cheekes and ſhame╌faſt Ro╌ſes: Her louely cheekes her eyes two Comets blazing. Come downe from heauen with beauties grace a╌ma╌zing: Come downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, with beauties grace amazing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:6"/>
                  <head>VII. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Lora faire loue I languiſh, For loue Flora for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, Flora faire loue I languiſh. For loue Flora for anguiſh. And thou doſt not thy duty, To be ſo nice for beauty. ii. for beauty I die I die, yet dying thus will I complaine me. ij Flora gentle and faire, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me. ii. Flora gentile and faire, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me. ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:7"/>
                  <head>VIII. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y hart why haſt thou taken, And forgot, &amp; forſaken, ij. forgot and forſaken, My hart why haſt thou taken, And forgot &amp; forſaken, ij. forgot, &amp; forſaken. Thou doeſt it leaſt in ſpi╌red, with his incloſed flames, thy hart be╌fi╌red, with his inclo╌ſed flames, thy hart be fi╌red fired, thy hart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired, with his incloſed, flames with his inclo╌ſed flames thy hart befi╌red, with his inclo ſed flames thy hart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired, befired.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:7"/>
                  <head>IX. CANTVS</head>
                  <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Till it frieth, Yet my hart neuer dieth, neuer di╌eth, my heart neuer dieth, yet my hart ne╌uer dieth, neuer dieth, yet my hart neuer dieth, my hart neuer dieth, my hart neuer di╌eth. Ah that my loue hath not ſome mortall firing, ii. ſome mortall firing. And that no ſtormes may quench, ij. His hart in╌ſpi╌ring, ij. His hart inſpiring. And that no ſtreames may quench, ij. His hart inſpi╌ring, his hart inſpi╌ring, his hart inſpi╌ring.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:8"/>
                  <head>X. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Iſſe me mine only Iewell, ij. And ſweetly kiſſing: Swathele me ſo that I may run a gaſping. ij. Die in your white armes &amp; your loue╌ly claſ╌ping, Dye in your white armes, Die in your white armes and your loue╌ly, claſping.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:8"/>
                  <head>XI. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Lodouico <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iadana.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aine would I dye for verie ſhame and ſorrow, for very ſhame &amp; ſorrow, ii. Faine would I dye for very ſhame and ſorrow, ii. for ve╌ry ſhame &amp; ſorrow. That day that I behold not Flora brightſom, ii. More ſhine then the ſun, ii. my loadſtar lightſom, ii. That day that I behold not Flora bright╌ſome. More ſhine then the ſun my loadſtar lightſom, ij.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:9"/>
                  <head>XII. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome ſhepheards god: come come come cloſly creeping, cloſly creeping, ſweetly lies here (a)ſlee╌ping. Come ſhepheards god come come come cloſly cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, cloſly creeping ſweetly lies here a ſlee╌ping. And Daphnis creepeth, creepeth, ij. Euen where thy true loue ſlee╌peth, And Daphnis creepeth, Euen where thy true loue ſleepeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:9"/>
                  <head>XIII. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Eeary and windles running, wounded eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a Deare, ij. in foreſt chaſed: Such are my ſenſes changing, reſtles as in a wood, ij. I ſtand ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. But when I thinke of thee what I haue ſpoken, of thee what I haue ſpoken. By gift of hand and hart there faith is broken, But when I thinke of thee what I haue ſpoken, of thee what I haue ſpoken, By gift of hand and hart, there faith is broken.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:10"/>
                  <head>XIIII. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Iraculous loues woun╌ding, ij. Miraculous loues woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: ij. Euen thoſe darts my ſweet <hi>Phillis,</hi> So fiercely ſhot againſt my hart reboun╌ding. Are turnd to Roſes Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olets and Lillies, ij. with oder ſweet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding, with oder ſweet abounding: Miraculous loues woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ii. Miraculous loues wounding, ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:10"/>
                  <head>XV. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aſt by a brooke I laid me, Lamenting griefe &amp;care, ij. Lamenting griefe and care, ii. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none could ayd me. Faſt by a brook I laid me Lamenting griefe &amp; care, ii. Lamenting griefe &amp; care, ii. When none could ayd me. Except ſome boult of thunder, ii. to burſt in ſunder, Forced my hart ſo penſiue, ii. to burſt in ſunder: Except ſome bolt of thunder ii. to burſt in ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, Forced my hart ſo pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiue ii. to burt in ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:11"/>
                  <head>XVI. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen loe by breake of mor╌ning, My loue hirſelfe adorning, when loe by breake of morning, My loue hirſelfe adorning, ij. Doth walke the woods ſo dainty, Gathring ſweet violets and cowſlips plenty, ij. The birds enamourd, ij. Sing and praiſe my <hi>Flo╌ra,</hi> Lo here a new <hi>Aurora,</hi> The birds enamourd, ij. ſing and praiſe my <hi>Flo╌ra.</hi> Lo here a new <hi>Aurora.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:11"/>
                  <head>XVII. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ong hath my loue bene kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my de╌lighting, ij. Long hath my loue been kept from my deligh╌ting, from my deligh╌ting, And with her abſence lingring ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled, Increaſe my griefe becauſe ſhe hath rebelled. All my ſweet requeſting, ij. All my ſweet requeſting, Ile loue no more but fall to deepe deteſting, ji. All my ſweet requeſting, ij. requeſting, Ile loue no more but fall to deepe deteſting ij.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:12"/>
                  <head>XVIII. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Earle, Chriſtal, gold and Ruby, Are ſacred gifts too baſe, ii. for ſuch as you be, ii. Pearle Chriſtal, Gold and Ruby, Are ſacred gifts too baſe, ii. for ſuch as you be, ii. Nature in thee her graces, ii. ſo firmely planted, woſe loue thou haſt not wan╌ted, O faire <hi>Eudora,</hi> ſtar of heauens light╌nes Firme fixed there thou ſhinſt moſt oriant brightnes, ii. O faire <hi>Eudora</hi> ſtar of heauens light╌neſſe, Firme fixed there thou ſhineſt. ii. moſt oriant brightnes</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:12"/>
                  <head>XIX. CANTVS</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Eaſe ſheapheards ceaſe I pray you, ii. For <hi>Coridon</hi> you neede not moue, who minds not to deany you, ii. when Apples, Peares, and Cheſtnuts be a ripe╌ning, hele giue vs leaue to daunce and here the piping, ii. hele giue vs leaue to daunce and here the piping, ii. when Apples, Peares, and Cheſtnuts be a ri╌ping, hele giue vs leaue to dance &amp; here the piping, ii. and here the pi╌ping, ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:13"/>
                  <head>XX. CANTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Aphne</hi> the bright when frankly ſhe deſired with <hi>Thirsis</hi> her ſweete hart to haue exſpired, <hi>Daphne</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bright when frankly ſhe deſired with <hi>Thirsis</hi> her ſweet hart to haue exſpired. Sweete (thus fell ſhe a crying) fell ſhe a crying. Sweet (thus fell ſhe a cry╌ing.) Dye for I am a dying, I am a dying: ij. Dye for I am a dying I am a dying. ij.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:13"/>
                  <p>CANZONETS. OR LITTLE SHORT SONGS TO FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>OYCES: CELECTED OVT OF the beſt and approued Italian Authors. BY THOMAS MORLEY, Gent. of her Maieſties Chappell.</p>
                  <p>ALTVS.</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by Peter Short, dwelling on Bredſtreet hill at the ſigne of the Star &amp; are there to be ſold. 1597.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:14"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:14"/>
                  <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL <hi>MAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER HENRIE TAPS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FIELD</hi> CITIZEN AND GRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CER OF THE CITTIE OF LONDON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all enormities reigning (in men of reaſonable capacitie) none maketh them more deformed then the monſter Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? whoſe outragious cruelty hath Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomorphoſed, <hi>friendſhip</hi> into <hi>emnity, familiarity,</hi> into <hi>contempt, Loue</hi> into <hi>hatred:</hi> and generally all <hi>good</hi> into <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> The remembrance whereof, hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtirred my ſences to haue your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in remembrance, for diuers and many curteſies, from you to my ſelfe and my friends often receaued: And that in bounty ſo farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as my offer of requitall can no way counteruaile. But as migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>Alexander,</hi> for tenne talents giuen to the reliefe of a poore craftes man, was thankefully contented with the receipt of a ſimple roote. So J hartily intreat you, to accept theſe poore Canzonets, by me collected from diuers excellent Jtalian Authours, for the honeſt recreation of your ſelfe and others: Such as in my ſimple iudgment are worthie the collecting, but much more worthy hauing the Habit of ſo worthy a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, in whoſe acceptance they ſhall bee ſo well entertained, as were their maſters preſent to behold it, they woulde not onely thinke them happely beſtowed, but alſo yeeld me thankes for choiſe of their patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. And thus crauing your worthy acceptance, but reſting ſtil your debtor, J take my leaue as yours to commaund.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>THOMAS MORLEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:15"/>
                  <head>A TABLE OF ALL THE CANZONETS contained in this BOOKE.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>NOw that each creature. I</item>
                     <item>Since that the time of fleeting. II.</item>
                     <item>Lady let me behold euer your beauty. III.</item>
                     <item>Lo Lady for your loue. IIII.</item>
                     <item>Fine dainty girle delightſome. V.</item>
                     <item>White Lillies be her cheekes. VI.</item>
                     <item>Flora faire loue I languiſh. VII</item>
                     <item>My hart why haſt thou taken. VIII.</item>
                     <item>Still it frieth. IX.</item>
                     <item>Kiſſe me mine only Iewell. X.</item>
                     <item>Faine would I die for very ſhame &amp; ſorrow. XI.</item>
                     <item>Come ſhepheards god. XII.</item>
                     <item>Weary and windles running. XIII.</item>
                     <item>Miraculous loues wounding. XIIII.</item>
                     <item>Faſt by a brooke <hi>I</hi> layd me. XV.</item>
                     <item>VVhen loe by breake of morning. XVI.</item>
                     <item>Long hath my loue. XVII.</item>
                     <item>Pearle, Chriſtall, Gold and Ruby. XVIII.</item>
                     <item>Ceaſe ſhepheards. XIX.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Daphne</hi> the bright. XX.</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:15"/>
                  <head>I. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow that each creature takes his reſt and ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth. ij. More wretched I then any worme that creepeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> creepeth. Alone all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortles vntill the morrow. Go recounting my ſorrow, my ſorrow. Goe recoun╌ting my ſorrow: ij. Goe recounting my ſorrow, my ſorrow, Goe recoun╌ting my ſorow. ij.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:16"/>
                  <head>II. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince that the time of fleeting, From thee is come my ſweeting: Since that the time of fleeting, From thee is come my ſweeting. Doe but a kiſſe award me: And for my ſeruiſe ſo you ſhall reward me, you ſhall reward me. Doe but a kiſſe award me, And for my ſeruiſe ſo you ſhall reward me, you ſhall reward me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:16"/>
                  <head>III. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ady let me behold, ij. euer your beauty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ii. Lady let me behold, ii. euer your beauty. ii. And ſeeke yee not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me ſo to enſtrang it, Since time to come may change it: ii. And ſeeke ye not from me ſo to enſtrange it, Since time to come may chang it ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:17"/>
                  <head>IIII. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>O Lady for your loue I feele this burning, I feele this burning, Lo Lady for your loue I feele this burning, I feele this burning. And no whit grieue you, ij. for this flaming fuell, when you deny me (O cruel). After a thouſand skorns one ſweet eye tur╌ning, one ſweet eye ij. turning, when you deny me, (O cruell.) After a thouſand skornes one ſweet eye turning, one ſweet eye, ij turning.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:17"/>
                  <head>V. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ine dainty girle delightſome, You be my Loadſtarre lightſome, ij. fine dainty girle delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, you be my loadſtar lightſom, ij. To you my hart ay turneth, when in the tempeſt, ij. when in the tempeſt of fierce loue it burneth, To you my hart ay turneth when in the tempeſt, ij. when in the tempeſt of fierce loue it burneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:18"/>
                  <head>VI. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hite Lillies be her cheekes &amp; ſhame╌faſt Ro╌ſes, White Lillies be her cheekes and ſhamfaſt Roſes. ij. Her louely cheekes her eyes two Comets blazing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Come downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, with beauties grace amazing: Come downe from heauen with beauties grace amazing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:18"/>
                  <head>VII. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Lora faire loue I languiſh, For loue Flora for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, Flora faire loue I languiſh. For loue Flora for anguiſh. And thou doſt not thy duty, To be ſo nice for beauty, ij. I die, yet dying thus will I complaine me ii. Will I complaine me, Flora gentle and faire, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me, oh ſhe hath ſlain me. ii. Flora gentile and faire oh ſhe hath ſlaine me. ii. oh ſhe hath ſlain me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:19"/>
                  <head>VIII. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y hart why haſt thou taken why haſt thou ta╌ken, And forgot, &amp; forſaken, forſaken, and forgot, &amp; forſaken: My hart why haſt thou taken, why haſt thou taken: And forgot &amp; forſaken, forſaken, And forgot, &amp; forſaken. Thou doeſt it leaſt inſpi╌red with his inclo╌ſed flames, with his inclo╌ſed flames, thy hart be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, with his inclo╌ſed, flames thy hart befi╌red, be╌fired, with his incloſed flames, thy hart be╌fi╌red with his inclo╌ſed flames thy hart be╌fi╌red, fired, thy hart be╌fired</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:19"/>
                  <head>IX. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Till it flieth, yet my hart neuer dieth neuer di╌eth: yet my heart neuer dieth, yet my hart neuer dieth, neuer dieth. Ah that my loue hath not ſome mortall firing, ij. ſome mortall firing. And that no ſtormes may quench. ij. His hart inſpi╌ring, his hart in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, His hart inſpi╌ring: And that no ſtormes may quench ij. His hart inſpi╌ring. ij. His hart inſpiring.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:20"/>
                  <head>X. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Iſſe me mine only Iewell, ij. Swathele me ſo that I may run a gaſping, ij. ſwathele me ſo, ſwathele me ſo that I may run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſping: Die in your white armes, Die in your white armes &amp; your louely claſ╌ping, Dye in your white armes and your loue╌ly claſping, Die in your white armes and your louely claſping.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:20"/>
                  <head>XI. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Lodouico <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iadana.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aine would I dye for verie ſhame and ſorrow, ii. for ve╌ry ſhame &amp; ſorrow, faine would I dye for very ſhame and ſorrow, for verie ſhame &amp; ſorrow. ii. That day that I behold not Flora bright╌ſome, More ſhine then the ſun my loadſtar lightſom. ii. That day that I behold not Flora brightſom. ii. More ſhine then the ſun, ii. my loadſtar brightſom, ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:21"/>
                  <head>XII. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome ſhepheards god: come come come cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cree╌ping, Narciſcus mother ſweetly ij. lies here ſleeping. Come ſhepheards god come come com cloſly cree╌ping, Narciſcus mother ſweetly. ij. lies here ſleeping: And Daphnis creepeth Euen where thy true loue ſleepeth, And Daphnis creepeth, creepeth, ij. Euen where thy true loue ſlee╌peth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:21"/>
                  <head>XIII. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Eeary and windles running, wounded eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a Deare, ij. in foreſt chaſed: ii. Such are my ſenſes changing, reſtles as in a wood, ij. I ſtand amazed. ii. But when I thinke of thee what thou haſt ſpoken, of thee what thou haſt ſpoken. By gift of hand and hart, there faith, ii. is broken, But when I thinke of thee what thou haſt ſpoken, of thee what thou haſt ſpoken, By gift of hand and hart, there faith, ii. is broken.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:22"/>
                  <head>XIIII. ALTVS</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Iraculous loues wounding, ij. Miraculous loues woun╌ding: ij. Euen thoſe darts my ſweet <hi>Phillis,</hi> So fiercely ſhot againſt my hart rebounding. Are turnd to Roſes Violets and Lil╌lies, Violets and Roſes with oder ſweet abounding, ii. Miraculous loues wounding, ii. Miraculous loues woun╌ding. ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:22"/>
                  <head>XV. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aſt by a brooke I laid me, Lamenting griefe &amp;care, ij. Lamenting griefe and care, ii. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none could ayd me. Faſt by a brook I laid me Lamenting griefe &amp; care, ii. Lamenting griefe and care, ij. When none could ayd me. Except ſome boult of thunder, Forced my hart ſo penſiue, ii. ii. to burſt in ſun╌der: Except ſome bolt of thunder, Forced my hart ſo pen╌ſiue ii. Forced my hart ſo pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiue to burt in ſun╌der.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:23"/>
                  <head>XVI. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen loe by breake of morning, My loue hir ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning, ij. when loe by breake of mor╌ning, My loue hir ſelfe adorning, Doth walke the woods ſo dainty, Gathring ſweet violets and cow╌ſlips plenty, ij. &amp; cowſlips plenty. The birds enamour'd, ij. Sing and praiſe my <hi>Flo╌ra,</hi> Lo here a new <hi>Aurora,</hi> The birds en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amour'd ij. ſing and praiſe my <hi>Flo╌ra.</hi> Lo here anew <hi>Aurora.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:23"/>
                  <head>XVII. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ong hath my loue bene kept from my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligh╌ting, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my de╌lighting, Long hath my loue been kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my de╌ligh╌ting, ij. And with her abſence lingring ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled, Increaſe my griefe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe hath rebel╌led. All my ſweet requeſting, ij. I'le loue no more but fall to deepe deteſting ij. All my ſweet requeſting, ij. All my ſweet requeſting, I'le loue no more but fall to deepe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:24"/>
                  <head>XVIII. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Earle, Chriſtal, gold and Ruby, Are ſacred gifts too baſe, ii. for ſuch as you be, ii. Pearle Chriſtal, Gold and Ruby, Are ſacred gifts too baſe, ii. for ſuch as you be, ii. Nature in thee her graces, ii. ſo firmly planted, whoſe loue y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt not wanted, O faire <hi>Eudora,</hi> ſtar of heauens light╌nes: Firme fixed there thou ſhineſt ii. moſt oriant brightnes, O faire <hi>Eudora,</hi> ſtarre of heauens light╌neſſe, Firme fixed there thou ſhinſt moſt oria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t brightneſſe. ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:24"/>
                  <head>XIX. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Eaſe ſheapheards ceaſe I pray you, ii. For <hi>Cori╌don</hi> you need not moue, you neede not moue, who minds not to denay you. ii. when Apples, Peares, and Cheſtnuts be a ripe╌ning, hele giue vs leaue to daunce and here the piping, hele giue vs leaue to daunce &amp; here the piping. ii. ii. when Apples, Peares, and Cheſtnuts be a ri╌ping, hele giue vs leaue to dance and here the piping, ii. hele giue vs leaue to dance, &amp; here the pi╌ping the piping.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:25"/>
                  <head>XX. ALTVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Aphne</hi> the bright when frankly ſhe de╌ſired with <hi>Thirsis</hi> her ſweet hart to haue exſpired, <hi>Daphne</hi> the bright when frankly ſhe de╌ſired with <hi>Thirsis</hi> her ſweet hart to haue exſpired. Sweete (thus fell ſhe acrying:) Sweet (thus fell ſhe acry╌ing, Dye for I am a dying, ij. I am a dying: Dye for I am a dying, ij. I am a dying.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:25"/>
                  <p>CANZONETS. OR LITTLE SHORT SONGS TO FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>OYCES: CELECTED OVT OF the beſt and approued Italian Authors. BY THOMAS MORLEY, Gent. of her Maieſties Chappell.</p>
                  <p>TENOR.</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by Peter Short, dwelling on Bredſtreet hill at the ſigne of the Star &amp; are there to be ſold. 1597.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:26"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:26"/>
                  <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL <hi>MAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER HENRIE TAPS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FIELD</hi> CITIZEN AND GRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CER OF THE CITTIE OF LONDON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all enormities reigning (in men of reaſonable capacitie) none maketh them more deformed then the monſter Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? whoſe outragious cruelty hath Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomorphoſed, <hi>friendſhip</hi> into <hi>emnity, familiarity,</hi> into <hi>contempt, Loue</hi> into <hi>hatred:</hi> and generally all <hi>good</hi> into <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> The remembrance whereof, hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtirred my ſences to haue your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in remembrance, for diuers and many curteſies, from you to my ſelfe and my friends often receaued: And that in bounty ſo farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as my offer of requitall can no way counteruaile. But as migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>Alexander,</hi> for tenne talents giuen to the reliefe of a poore craftes man, was thankefully contented with the receipt of a ſimple roote. So J hartily intreat you, to accept theſe poore Canzonets, by me collected from diuers excellent Jtalian Authours, for the honeſt recreation of your ſelfe and others: Such as in my ſimple iudgment are worthie the collecting, but much more worthy hauing the Habit of ſo worthy a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, in whoſe acceptance they ſhall bee ſo well entertained, as were their maſters preſent to behold it, they woulde not onely thinke them happely beſtowed, but alſo yeeld me thankes for choiſe of their patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. And thus crauing your worthy acceptance, but reſting ſtil your debtor, J take my leaue as yours to commaund.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>THOMAS MORLEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <div n="2" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:27"/>
                  <head>II. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince that the time of fleeting, From thee is come my ſweeting, Since y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the time of fleeting, From thee is come my ſweeting. Do but a kiſſe award me, and for my ſeruice ſo you ſhall reward me, you ſhal re╌ward me. Do but a kiſſe award me, And for my ſeruice ſo you ſhall reward me, you ſhal re╌ward me</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:27"/>
                  <head>III. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ady, let me behold euer your beauty, ij. Ladie let me behold euer your beauty. Lady let me behold euer your beauty. ij. Lady let me behold euer your beauty. And ſeeke ye not from me ſo to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrange it, Since time to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e may change it, Since time to come may change it, And ſeeke ye not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me ſo to enſtrange it, Since time to come may chang it, Since time to come may change it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:28"/>
                  <head>IIII. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>O Lady for your loue I feele this burning, I feele this bur╌ning, Lo Lady for your loue I feele this burning, I feele this bur╌ning. And no white greeue you for this flaming fuell, when you deny mee (O cruell!) Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a thouſand skorns one ſweete eye turning, one ſweete eye turning, when you deny me (O cruell) After a thouſand skornes one ſweete eye turning, one ſweet eye turning.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:28"/>
                  <head>V. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ine dainty girle delightſom, You be my Loadſtar lightſom, my Loadſtar lightſome, fine dainty girle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightſom, you be my loadſtar lightſom, my loadſtar lightſom. To you my hart ay tur╌neth, when in the tem╌peſt of fierce loue it burneth, ij. To you my hart ay tur╌neth when in the tem╌peſt of fierce loue it bur╌neth. ij.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:29"/>
                  <head>VI. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hite Lillies be her cheekes &amp; ſhamefaſt Roſes, white Lillies be her cheekes and ſhame╌faſt Ro╌ſes: ij. White Lillies be her cheekes and ſhame╌faſt Ro╌ſes. Her louely cheekes her eyes two Comets blazing. Come downe from heauen, ij. with beauties grace a ma╌zing: Come downe from heauen ij. with beauties grace a╌ma╌zing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:29"/>
                  <head>VII. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Lora faire loue I languiſh, For loue Flora for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, Flora faire loue I languiſh. For loue Flora for anguiſh And thou doſt not thy duty, To be ſo nice for beauty. ii. I die I die, yet dying thus will I complaine me ii. Flora gentle and faire, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me. ii. Flora gentile and faire, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me. ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:30"/>
                  <head>VIII. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y hart why haſt thou taken, thou taken, And forgot, &amp; forſaken, forgot &amp; forſa╌ken, My hart why haſt thou taken, thou taken: And forgot &amp; forſaken, forgot, &amp; forſaken. Thou doeſt it leaſt in ſpi╌red, with his in╌cloſed flames, thy hart be╌fired, with his in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clo╌ſed flames, thy hart befi╌red, thy hart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired, ij. with his incloſed, flames thy hart be╌fired, with his inclo╌ſed flames, thy hart be╌fi╌red thy hart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired, ij</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:30"/>
                  <head>IX. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Till it flieth, ij. Yet my hart neuer di╌eth, ne╌uer dieth, yet my heart neuer di╌eth, neuer di╌eth, yet my hart ne╌uer di╌eth my hart neuer di╌eth. Ah that my loue hath not ſome mortall firing, ii. ſome mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall fi╌ring. And that no ſtormes may quench. ij. His hart inſpiring, ij. His hart inſpiring, And that no ſtormes may quench, ij. His hart inſpiring, ij. His hart inſpiring. ij.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:31"/>
                  <head>X. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Iſſe me mine only Iewell, Swathele me ſo that I may run a gaſ╌ping, ij. Swathele me ſo that I may runne a gaſping, run a gaſping. Die in your white armes &amp; your louely claſping. ij. Dye in your white armes and your louely, Die in your white armes and your louely claſping.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:31"/>
                  <head>XI. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Lodouico <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iadana.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aine would I dye for verie ſhame and ſorrow, ii. &amp; ſor╌row, faine would I dye for very ſhame and ſorrow, ii. &amp; ſor╌row. That day y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I behold not Flora bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, More ſhine then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſun my loadſtar lightſom, my load╌ſtar light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom: That day that I behold not Flora bright╌ſom. More ſhine then the ſun my loadſtar lightſom, my load╌ſtar lightſome.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:32"/>
                  <head>XII. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome ſhepheards god: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly creeping, Narciſcus mother ij. ſweetly lies a ſleeping Come ſhepheards god come come come cloſ╌ly creeping, Narciſcus mother ij. ſweetly lies a ſleeping. And Daphnis creepeth, ii. And Daphnis creepeth, Euen where thy true loue thy true loue ſleepeth, And Daphnis cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, ii. And Daphnis crepeth, Euen where thy true loue thy true loue ſleepeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:32"/>
                  <head>XIII. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Eeary: and windles running, wounded euen as a Deare, ij. in for╌reſt chaſed: My ſenſes changing, reſtles as in a wood, ii. I ſtand amazed But when I think of thee what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſpoken, of thee what thou haſt ſpoken. By gift of hand and hart, ii. there faith is bro╌ken, But when I thinke of thee what thou haſt ſpoken, of thee what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſpoken, By gift of hand and hart, ii. there faith is bro╌ken.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:33"/>
                  <head>XIIII. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Iraculous loues wounding, ij. Miraculous loues wounding: ij. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe darts my ſweet <hi>Phillis,</hi> So fiercely ſhot againſt my hart rebounding, againſt my hart rebounding, my hart rebou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, Are turnd to Roſes Violets &amp; Lillies, with oder ſweet abounding, with oder ſweet a╌bounding, Miraculous loues wounding, ii. Miraculous loues woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:33"/>
                  <head>XV. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aſt by a brooke I laid me, Lamenting griefe &amp; care, ij. Lamenting griefe and care, when none could ayd me. Faſt by a brook I laid me, Lamenting grief &amp; care ii. Lamenting griefe and care when none could ayd me. Except ſome boult of thunder, to burſt in ſunder, ii. Forced my hart ſo penſiue, to burſt in ſunder: Except ſome bolt of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to burſt in ſunder. ii. Forced my hart ſo penſiue to burſt in ſunder.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:34"/>
                  <head>XVI. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen loe by breake of morning, My loue hir ſelfe ador╌ning, when loe by breake of morning, My loue hir ſelfe ador╌ning, Doth walk the woods ſo dainty, Gathring ſweet violets and cowſlips plenty, ij. The birds enamour'd, ij. Lo here a new <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro╌ra,</hi> The birds enamour'd ij. Lo here a new <hi>Auro╌ra.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:34"/>
                  <head>XVII. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ong hath my loue bene kept from my delighting, ij. Long hath my loue been kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my delighting, ij. And with her abſence lingring ſo compel╌led, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſt my griefe becauſe ſhe hath rebelled. But ſince ſhe ſcorneth all my ſweet requeſting, I'le loue no more but fall to deep deteſting, ii. But ſince ſhe ſcorneth all my ſweet requeſting, I'le loue no more but fall to deep deteſting ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:35"/>
                  <head>XVIII. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Earle, Chriſtal, gold and Ruby, Are ſacred gifts to baſe, ii. for ſuch as you be, ii. Pearle Chriſtal, Gold, &amp; Ru╌by, Are ſacred gifts too baſe, ii. for ſuch as you be. ii. Nature in thee her graces, ſo firmly planted whoſe loue y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt not wan╌ted, O faire <hi>Eudora,</hi> ſtar of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lightnes Firme fixed there y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhinſt ii. moſt oriant bright╌nes, ii. O faire <hi>Eudora</hi> ſtar of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lightnes, Firm fixed there y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhin'ſt ij. moſt oria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bright╌neſſe. ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:35"/>
                  <head>XIX. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Eaſe ſheapheards ceaſe I pray you, ii. For <hi>Cori╌don</hi> you need not moue who minds not to denay you. ii. When Apples, Peares, and Cheſtnuts be a ripening, Hele giue vs leaue to dance and here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> piping, ii. hele giue vs leaue to dance &amp; here the piping, &amp; heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pi╌ping. When Apples, peares, &amp; Cheſtnuts, be a riping, hele giue vs leaue to dance &amp; here the piping, ii. hele giue vs leaue to dance &amp; here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> piping &amp; here the pi╌ping, the pi╌ping.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:36"/>
                  <head>XX. TENOR.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Aphne</hi> the bright when frankly ſhe de╌ſired with <hi>Thirsis</hi> her ſweet hart to haue exſpired, <hi>Daphne</hi> the bright when frankly ſhe deſi╌red with <hi>Thirsis</hi> her ſweet hart to haue exſpi╌red. Sweete (thus fell ſhe acry╌ing:) fell ſhe acrying, ij. Dye for I am a dying ij. Dye for I am a dying ij.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:36"/>
                  <p>CANZONETS. OR LITTLE SHORT SONGS TO FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>OYCES: CELECTED OVT OF the beſt and approued Italian Authors. BY THOMAS MORLEY, Gent. of her Maieſties Chappell.</p>
                  <p>BASSVS.</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at London by Peter Short, dwelling on Bredſtreet hill at the ſigne of the Star &amp; are there to be ſold. 1597.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:37"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:37"/>
                  <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL <hi>MAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STER HENRIE</hi> TAPS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FIELD CITIZEN AND GRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CER OF THE CITTIE OF LONDON.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all enormities reigning (in men of reaſonable capacitie) none maketh them more deformed then the monſter Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? whoſe outragious cruelty hath Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomorphoſed, <hi>friendſhip</hi> into <hi>emnity, familiarity,</hi> into <hi>contempt, Loue</hi> into <hi>hatred:</hi> and generally all <hi>good</hi> into <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> The remembrance whereof, hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtirred my ſences to haue your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in remembrance, for diuers and many curteſies, from you to my ſelfe and my friends often receaued: And that in bounty ſo farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as my offer of requitall can no way counteruaile. But as migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>Alexander,</hi> for tenne talents giuen to the reliefe of a poore craftes man, was thankefully contented with the receipt of a ſimple roote. So J hartily intreat you, to accept theſe poore Canzonets, by me collected from diuers excellent Jtalian Authours, for the honeſt recreation of your ſelfe and others: Such as in my ſimple iudgment are worthie the collecting, but much more worthy hauing the Habit of ſo worthy a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, in whoſe acceptance they ſhall bee ſo well entertained, as were their maſters preſent to behold it, they woulde not onely thinke them happely beſtowed, but alſo yeeld me thankes for choiſe of their patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. And thus crauing your worthy acceptance, but reſting ſtil your debtor, J take my leaue as yours to commaund.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>THOMAS MORLEY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:38"/>
                  <head>A TABLE OF ALL THE <hi>CANZONETS contained in this BOOKE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <item>NOw that each creature. I</item>
                     <item>Since that the time of fleeting. II.</item>
                     <item>Lady let me behold euer your beauty. III.</item>
                     <item>Lo Lady for your loue. IIII.</item>
                     <item>Fine dainty girle delightſome. V.</item>
                     <item>White Lillies be her cheekes. VI.</item>
                     <item>Flora faire loue I languiſh. VII</item>
                     <item>My hart why haſt thou taken. VIII.</item>
                     <item>Still it frieth. IX.</item>
                     <item>Kiſſe me mine only Iewell. X.</item>
                     <item>Faine would I die for very ſhame &amp; ſorrow. XI.</item>
                     <item>Come ſhepheards god. XII.</item>
                     <item>Weary and windles running. XIII.</item>
                     <item>Miraculous loues wounding. XIIII.</item>
                     <item>Faſt by a brooke <hi>I</hi> layd me. XV.</item>
                     <item>VVhen loe by breake of morning. XVI.</item>
                     <item>Long hath my loue. XVII.</item>
                     <item>Pearle, Chriſtall, Gold and Ruby. XVIII.</item>
                     <item>Ceaſe ſhepheards. XIX.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Daphne</hi> the bright. XX.</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:38"/>
                  <head>I. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow that each creature takes his reſt and ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, ij. More wretched I then any worme that creepeth, Alone all comfortles vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the morrow, Goe recounting my ſorrow, ij. Goe recounting my ſorrow, Goe recounting my ſorrow, ij. Goe recounting my ſorrow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:39"/>
                  <head>II. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince that the time of fleeting, From thee is come my ſweeting, Since that the time of fleeting, From thee is come my ſweeting, Do but a kiſſe award me, and for my ſeruice ſo you ſhall award me, you ſhal reward me, Do but a kiſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward me, And for my ſeruice ſo you ſhal reward me, you ſhal reward me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:39"/>
                  <head>III. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ady, let me behold euer your beauty, ij. Ladie let me behold euer your beauty, ij. And ſeeke ye not from me ſo to enſtrange it, Since time to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e may change it, Since time to come may change it, And ſeeke ye not from me ſo to enſtrange it, Since time to come may change it, Since to to come may change it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:40"/>
                  <head>IIII. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>O Lady for your loue I feele this burning, I feele this burning, Loe Lady for your loue I feele this burning, I feele this burning. And no whit greeue you for this fla╌ming fuel, when you deny me (O Cruell!) After a thouſand skorns one ſweeet eye turning, one ſweet eye turning, when you deny me (O cruell After a thouſand skornes one ſweete eye turning, one ſweet eye turning</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:40"/>
                  <head>V. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ine daintie girle: You be my loadſtarre lightſome, you be my Loadſtarre lightſome, you be my Loadſtarre lightſome, you be my loadſtarre lightſome. When in the tempeſt, ij. when in the tempeſt of fierce loue it burneth, when in the tempeſt, ij. when in the tempeſt of fierce loue it burneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:41"/>
                  <head>VI. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouani Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hite Lillies be her cheekes &amp; ſhamefaſt Roſes,and ſham╌faſt Ro╌ſes: White Lillies be her cheekes and ſhamfaſt Roſes and ſhame╌faſt ro╌ſes. Her loue╌ly cheekes her eyes two Comets blazing, Come downe from heauen with beauties grace ama╌zing: Come downe from heauen with beauties grace ama╌zing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:41"/>
                  <head>VII. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Lora: For loue Flora for anguiſh, ij. And thou doſt not thy duty, To be ſo nice for bauty ij. I die, yet dying thus will I complaine me. ij. Flora gentle and faire oh ſhe hath ſlaine me, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me, Flora gentle and faire oh ſhe hath ſlaine me, oh ſhe hath ſlaine me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:42"/>
                  <head>VIII. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y hart: And forgot, and forſaken, ij And forgot, and forſaken: ij. Thou doeſt it leaſt in ſpi╌red with his inclo╌ſed flames thy hart be fi╌red with his incloſed flames, with his inclo╌ſed, flames thy hart befired, with his inclo╌ſed flames, thy hart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi╌red with his incloſed flames, with his in╌cloſed flames thy hart be╌fi╌red.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:42"/>
                  <head>IX. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Till it frieth. ij. Yet my heart ne╌uer dieth, neuer dieth: Yet my heart nee╌uer di╌eth. ij. Ah that my loue hath not ſome mortall firing, ij. ſome mortall firing. And that no ſtormes may quench. ij. His hart inſpiring. ij. His hart inſpiring. And that no ſtormes may quench. ii. His hart inſpiring. ii. His hart in╌ſpi╌ring.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:43"/>
                  <head>X. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Baſſano.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Iſſe me mine only Iewell, ij. Kiſſe me mine onely Iewell and ſweetly kiſſing, Swathele me ſo that I may run a gaſping, ſwathele me ſo, ſwathele me ſo that I may run a gaſping: Die in your white armes &amp; your louely claſping, Dye in your white armes and your louely claſ╌ping.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:43"/>
                  <head>XI. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Lodouice viadana.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aine would I dye for verie ſhame and ſorrow, for ve╌ry ſhame &amp; ſorrow, faine would I dye for very ſhame and ſorrow, for ve╌rie ſhame and ſorrow. That day that I behold not Flora brightſome, Flora brightſome. More ſhine then the ſunne my Load╌ſtarre lightſome: That day that I behold not Flora brightſome Flora brightſome, More ſhine then the ſunne my Load╌ſtarre lightſome.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:44"/>
                  <head>XII. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome ſhepheards god: Narciſcus mother ſweetly ij. lies here ſleeping. Narciſcus mother ſweetly. ij. lies here ſleeping, And Daphnis cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth. ij. And Daphnis creepeth Euen where thy true loue ſleepeth, And Daphnis creepeth. ij. And Daphnis creepeth Euen where thy true loue ſleepeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:44"/>
                  <head>XIII. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Eeary: and windles running, wounded euen as a Deare, ij. in for╌reſt chaſed: Such are my ſenſes changing, reſtles as in a wood, ii. I ſtand amazed. But when I think of thee what thou haſt ſpoken, of thee what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſpoken. By gift of hand &amp; hart there faith is broken, But when I think of thee what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt ſpoken, of thee what thou haſt ſpoken, By gift of hand and hart their faith is broken.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:45"/>
                  <head>XIIII. BASSVS</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Iraculous loues wounding, Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous loues wounding: Euen thoſe darts my ſweet <hi>Phillis,</hi> So fiercely ſhot againſt my hart rebounding. Are turnd to Roſes, Violets and Lil╌lies, Violets and Lillies, with oder ſweet abounding, with oder ſweet abounding, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous loues wounding, Miraculous loues wounding.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:45"/>
                  <head>XV. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Horatio Vecchi.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aſt by a brooke. Lamenting griefe &amp; care, ij. when none could ayd me Lamenting grief &amp; care ii. when none could ayd me. Except ſome boult of thunder, Forced my hart ſo penſiue, to burſt in ſunder: ii. Except ſome bolt of thunder Forced my hart ſo penſiue to burſt in ſunder. ij.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:46"/>
                  <head>XVI. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loe by break of morning, My loue hir ſelfe hir ſelfe adorning, when loe by breake of morning, My loue hir ſelfe hir ſelfe adorning, Doth walk the woods ſo dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Gathring ſweet violets and cowſlips plenty, and Cowſlips plenty.The birds enamour'd, ſing and praiſe my <hi>Flora,</hi> Lo here a new <hi>Aurora,</hi> The birds enamour'd ſing and praiſe my <hi>Flora,</hi> Lo here a new <hi>Aurora.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:46"/>
                  <head>XVII. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ong hath my loue bene kept from my delighting, ij. Long hath my loue been kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my delighting, ij. And with her abſence lingring ſo compelled, But ſince ſhe ſcorneth all my ſweet requeſting, I'le loue no more but fall to deepe deteſting. ii. But ſince ſhe ſcorneth all my ſweet requeſting, I'le loue no more but fall to deepe deteſting ii.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:47"/>
                  <head>XVIII. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Earle, Chriſtal, gold and Ruby, Are ſacred gifts to baſe, ii. for ſuch as you be, Pearle Chriſtal, Gold, and Ruby, Are ſacred gifts too baſe, ii. for ſuch as you be. Nature in thee her graces, ſo firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly planted whoſe loue y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt not wanted, O faire <hi>Eudora,</hi> ſtar of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lightnes. Firme fixed there y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhinſt moſt or'ant brightnes, O faire <hi>Eudora</hi> ſtar of heauens lightnes, Firm fixed there thou ſhin'ſt moſt or'ant brightneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:47"/>
                  <head>XIX. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Felice Anerio.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Eaſe ſheapheards ceaſe I pray you, ii. For <hi>Coridon</hi> you neede not moue who minds not to denay you. ii. When Apples, Pears, and Cheſtnuts be a riping, Hele giue vs leaue to dance and here the piping, ij. hele giue vs leaue to dance &amp; here the piping, the piping. When Apples, peares, &amp; Cheſtnuts, be a riping, hele giue vs leaue to dance &amp; here the piping, ii. hele giue vs leaue to dance and here the piping the piping.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="canzonet">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:48"/>
                  <head>XX. BASSVS.</head>
                  <byline>Giouanni Croce.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="music">
                        <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Aphne</hi> the bright when frankly ſhe deſired with <hi>Thirsis</hi> her ſweet hart to haue exſpired, <hi>Daphne</hi> the bright when frankly ſhe deſired with <hi>Thirsis</hi> her ſweet hart to haue exſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Sweet (thus fell ſhe a crying:) ij. fell ſhe a crying, Die for I am a dying, I am a dying, Dye for I am a dying, I am a dying.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10603:48"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
